[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio net se radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software is an open source project
that abstracts CPU memory storage and
other compute resources away from
machines enabling fault tolerant and
elastic distributed systems to easily be
built and run effectively Benjamin spent
time as a lead engineer at Twitter and
he now works at in mesosphere Ben
Heineman welcome to software engineering
radio thanks thanks so much for having
me in a talk that you gave you began
with a statement you're building a
distributed system paraphrasing mark
cabbage before we dive into meso
specifically I want to get a feeling for
how you think about the modern
distributed system architecture sure
that's that's a great question I think
it's really interesting because right
now pretty much everybody is building a
distributed system I think that's that's
that a mark mark cabbage article that
you're referencing most people don't
necessarily realize that they're
building distributed systems but it's
pretty inherent and most of the the
software designs that we have today
whether it be because the applications
we're building just need to be each
ability handle lots and lots of traffic
so you need to spread them across lots
of machines or whether you just need to
have many of them running at the same
time to deal with failures and so I
think it's it's it's kind of everyone's
basically building distribute system
even if perhaps you you you don't
realize it and I think what's really
interesting about that is distributed
systems are not really taught in most
formal computer science education at the
university that I went to for my
bachelor's degree at the University of
Washington I think there was a
distributed systems class if you were a
master student and maybe they're
starting to make that be a class for
undergrads but for the most part that's
not really taught so most people kind of
pick this up from either their
colleagues or book
or webpages or whatever it is and it's
tough stuff you know it's it's kind of
like parallel computing except there's
failures so it's it's even harder I
think really where we're at with
distributed systems today is we're at a
place where sort of and I I kind of have
talked about this before where we're
kind of the place where you used to have
to do your own memory management and I
don't mean like with C or C++ I mean
like when you actually had to pick which
regions of memory you wanted because the
operating system wasn't providing any
abstractions for you and then eventually
an operating system provided vmm virtual
memory managers which made things a lot
easier and that's kind of where we're at
today with distributed systems pretty
much everybody has to do everything
manually and almost everybody has to
reinvent the wheel which makes all the
the distributed systems we build that
much more brittle that much harder to
build and that much more likely to fail
so so that's kind of where I think we're
at today when it comes to distributed
systems and that's great because I think
that that means there's a big
opportunity that to make building
distribute systems even easier so talk a
little more about the analogy to virtual
memory for you know cuz because you know
when we were just developing on single
boxes and didn't have to deal with the
distributed system and then you know we
got this idea of virtual memory and like
oh it's it's great like we don't you
know you have this you actually now have
this Wellspring of memory available to
you and it's it's all abstract it away
from you so talk a little more about
that analogy and how may sews acts like
maybe the the virtual memory manager of
the of the data center operating system
sure sure yeah yeah so um I think I
think right now there are some things
that basically every every distributed
system ends up having to redo so for
example if you're building something and
you want to launch an application or a
process on some other machine because
you're distributed for the most part
your program that have that up
yourselves so you're you're figuring out
okay this is the Machine I want to
launch it to either somebody else has
launched another you know posess has
launched some kind of agent for me or I
even need to figure out how to first get
my tasks for my process
to that that other machine so that's one
example another example is leader
election pretty much every single
distribute system has some notion not
every but most have some notion of who
the current leader is and/or who the
current coordinator is and to figure
that stuff out
you really need to have some pretty
sophisticated algorithms for actually
determining who can be a leader and of
course in the face of failures this this
is even tougher so there are some tools
out there that help with that there are
things like zookeeper and SCD and these
can really help but which is great which
is great that case they're probably much
easier
but they're still there's still a lot of
a lot of work that you have to do and
there's a lot of tricky cases that you
still have to solve when you're when
you're using those systems so that's
another example another example would be
dealing with with failures so what does
it mean when I've distributed my work
and I've got some subtasks on some
machines and then those machines fail do
I actually know that the tasks have
failed can I decide okay that that task
is failed so I'm gonna go ahead and I'm
gonna launch another task reliably what
happens if that machine comes back and
actually my task is still running do I
need to take care of the fact that I
killed that task because I launched it
on a different machine so so you know
that's that's a pretty typical problem
in distributed systems there's sort of
there's the same you know you want to
make sure that you you shoot the other
process in the head when it comes back
and dealing with that is sort of a whole
nother aspect so that's just a couple
but these are the types of things that
we really try to provide as an
abstraction layer with with maysa so you
don't have to think about how you're
gonna get your task to a different
machine with maysa you just tell me says
hey run this task using these resources
those resources are tied to a particular
machine and then the tap and then maces
takes care of getting the tasks they're
starting the task up watching the task
while it's actually running on that
machine if that task fails telling the
distributed system hey this task has
failed or if the task if my whole
machine fails being able to determine
okay hey this machine fails telling the
distributed system that machine has
failed so you can reschedule your task
and of course of course if the machine
was actually just Network partitioned
away
when when when the machinery connects to
the system may suppose make sure hey I
actually told the distributed system
that this task was dead so even though
the task is still running the machine
was just network partitioned away I want
to make sure that I actually killed that
task because I told the system that it
was actually dead so this is where maysa
really comes in as an abstraction layer
where it provides these primitives that
building to be somebody building a
distributed system can take advantage of
and kind of not have to rebuild that
code themselves so they can focus quote
and I suppose on their business logic if
you will the business logic of the
distribute system and not a lot of those
those other pieces and sort of bringing
it back to the virtual machine manager
really what this what this the goal of
what this is trying to do is make people
more productive so make people be able
to focus on just the aspects of their
distribute systems and you to focus on
not a lot of the plumbing that that
that's really really important but not
everybody needs to actually build and
that's really what what operating
systems and kernels really provide is
they provide the abstractions that make
it easier for people to build their
software and build their systems without
everybody having to build the exact same
thing and you know I think that the the
virtual memory managers is such an
interesting example because so many
people actually never believed that the
vmm would ever be successful because
there's no way that something could come
in and actually abstract something like
this away and still get good performance
or always be correct and so a lot of
people that are sort of like no no no
we're never gonna use the vmm that's
that's not going to be something that's
real and computer scientists really
pushed it and said no no this is this is
the way that we should actually be
abstracting this and bringing our
software in the future and now it's just
something that we all take for granted
and I think that there's there is some
some similarities with distributed
systems as well I think some people
think do we really need these levels of
abstraction to really want these but I
think that since this is kind of still
even though the shared systems have been
along for a long time the early days of
district systems in the sense that more
and more people are building these
things every day now I think that we
will look back and we'll say hey yeah
there were a lot of abstractions that we
needed to put in place that really
really sort of helped us and and and
made us more productive and made our
code safer and crash
lasted more robust yeah what one thing I
think about as a total example of this
is like when I was in college I did take
a undergraduate class in distributed
systems and the entire class was about
you know like Paxos and like proving and
Relic writing proofs that you're like
distributed system was was fault
tolerant or you know if like you handle
all the error cases and whatnot and I
was like holy smokes just building a
distribute system is the worst thing in
the world I never ever want to do this
yeah and and none of the class was about
actually leveraging the distributed
system it was all about like here's all
the things you have to do in order to
ensure that a distributed system
actually works yeah and but but since
coming out of college and like you know
doing some of these shows on just some
of these distributed system applications
like oh this is so this is once once you
get this this stuff out of the way these
problems out of the way it becomes
awesome like you act you can actually
leverage this stuff um so you know when
you were when you were working on mezzos
what were the the idea is that that you
wanted to be able to leverage once you
had these these problems abstracted away
what are the what are the solutions that
you wanted maysa to make available to
programmers yeah that's that's good yeah
so um when we started the project we
were really focusing out that on at the
time was I dupe and what we really
wanted to enable was being able to
really two things one was run multiple
Hadoop's at the same time that was
actually that was our initial goal
because we were running a lot of hadoop
at berkeley we're doing a lot of
research with hadoop big data analytics
in particular was and still is a pretty
hot topic we yeah so basically just
wanted to enable a way to go to run
multiple loops so so why did we want to
run multiple DUP's well a couple of
reasons one we wanted better fault
isolation between the the Hadoop's that
were running so rather than when
somebody ends up writing a job that
triggers a bug and one of Hadoop and
crashes at Hadoop and all the hoops go
down we wanted to
to say have like a production Hadoop
that was running where the only jobs
that ran on that were jobs that we know
we've run for a long time and always
work and then we wanted to be able to
have an experimental the dupe where
anybody from from the lab could
basically just submit their own
MapReduce job and who knows what that's
kind of do if it's gonna bring down the
cluster if it's gonna suck up all the
resources but that's okay because that
independent Hadoop was not kind of
affect the production engine so I just
using multiple Hadoop's sort of on the
same file system or on the same same
data set that's exactly right that's
exactly right so take you know the nine
machines we had an eye and our cluster
and and basically say okay I'm gonna run
a production of dupe and I'm gonna run
an experimental Hadoop instance on these
same nine machines and but we wanted to
do it in a way where we said well rather
than taking these five machines for the
production instance and these four
machines for the experimental instance
what if we could do it in a way where
when the production instance needed five
machines it made sure that it got all
five of its machines but when it didn't
need those five once they had only
needed two then the experimental aduke
could use the other seven so we could
really dynamically and elastically move
the resources between the Hadoop the the
production Hadoop and the experimental
they do and so that's that's kind of
where it started and and we were really
focusing on sort of cluster managers of
the tasks there's been a lot of cluster
management and resource management
research that's happened in fact
projects like like PBS the portable
batch batch system dates back to I think
1991 so you know this wasn't new stuff
and in grid computing had been around
for a very long time and so we were
really looking at at cluster manager of
the past and saying okay well could we
use these things to sort of achieve our
goals of running multiple loops at the
same time and we realized that that no
there was there was a lot of opportunity
to make the idea of a cluster manager
much much better and in sort of doing
this we realized hey if we're going to
be putting this level of abstraction in
place in between you know the machines
are actually running and the distributed
systems the the Hadoop's on top that we
Ryan could we also then make it even
easier to build new distributed system
since kind of them that was the the
genesis of where we said wow yeah if we
put this this this level of instruction
in between we can also provide these
primitives to make it really really
easier to build other distribute systems
and that's why the one of the very first
distribute systems that we built on May
so sloths spark so spark which is now
also an Apache project and is is really
popular for big data analytics was a
distribute system that we built actually
in about a week on top of mesas and it
was kind of it was sort of the pet
project or footing were that that term
is but the example that the pet example
of hey yeah here's how you could build
pretty easily a distributed system on
marketing of streaming processor right
yeah so it does streaming it does
streaming but it also can do MapReduce
like batch like were closed as well the
really cool thing about SPARC is that
when we were building we decided let's
put everything in in-memory so when you
do your computations with often what was
the case with MapReduce is you run one
iteration of your job and it would read
everything from disk it would do if you
do the crunching and it would write this
stuff back to disk and then when you go
to do your second iteration of your job
you'd have to read everything from from
disk again so what we said with SPARC
was hey why don't we when we run jobs
why don't we keep the output in memory
so that when you run a second instance
of your job it can read the stuff from
memory again which is going to be far
far faster so we could do these
iterative jobs which were really really
typical in machine learning applications
no hundred times faster than then you
could do it on Hadoop because we
actually keep stuff in memory and and so
but really I think what was so
interesting for us at the time was hey
here was this hugest root system that we
whipped up that was you know fault
tolerant and highly available and we
could run it across thousands of
machines and it was like a thousand
lines of code or something like that and
of course spark has evolved considerably
since that day but a lot of the core
functionality the idea you know to put
this stuff in memory running it that
really really came from that that first
thousand lines of code so that was that
was kind of where sort of with you know
the history of the project where it came
from and you know your question was
about sort of what did we want to you
know really enable when when we were you
know the solutions we were trying trying
to enable when we first started working
on the project and I think the first
thing we're trying to do is just hey how
can we really effectively use resources
across multiple
distributed systems on the same data
center on the same set of resources at
the same time the same set of machines
at the same time and that really evolved
very quickly into well if the way that
we solve this is kind of kind of like a
cluster manager you know but again it's
a it's very much an evolution of cluster
management then we can at the same time
provide this abstraction layer or these
primitives for people to build other
distributed systems and that really open
the door into wow there's a lot more
things that we really want to enable
here not just people running Hadoop or
batch analytics but people running
running running and building whatever
distributed systems they really wanted
to and again we were really thinking
about analytics at the time so we were
thinking about MPI which is the message
passing interface which is still used
pretty heavily in National Labs and at
universities and that sort of evolved
and then we started thinking hey we
could just run we could run stateless
services we could run web servers we
could run web services we could run
anything that's kind of in the service
or architecture realm and that's when
Twitter actually really really picked up
my sauce was that when they said hey wow
we could we were they were interested in
decomposing their application into
something like a Sowa and they said well
we could use mesas to then run all these
these services and that evolved into not
just services but also mem caches and
Redis is and Jenkins for doing your CI
and your testing and your build and
pretty much more and more and more
applications and it just sort of sort of
evolved and to the point where we said
yeah you can pretty much run everything
on this you can run all your distribute
systems and and that's how we really
think about about about my sauce and
what we're doing at Mesa Sphere today is
enabling you to run any distributions
any applications just somewhere in your
data center that's great yeah so I want
to get into the the message passing
interface and the the nuts and bolts of
of how a sauce is implemented but before
that I want to talk a little more about
some examples of how maysa is being used
to give the listeners a finer
understanding of just a continual
iterate reiteration of of what exactly
are they are these problems that may
is solving you know you spoke about
Twitter maybe you could give a finer
explanation of Twitter's like set of
problems they had when they looked at
mesas and and maybe we could contrast
how these sets of problems that Twitter
would have been solved without meso sand
how they would have saw been and how
they actually got solved with meso so it
sort of to contrast the degree of the
value add that Mesa is providing sure
sure that's all it's great yeah so in
2010 I was asked to come over to Twitter
and give a talk in fact the entire team
that was working on it at Berkeley at
the time went over and we gave a talk
and we spoke to sort of the sort of the
researchy group at Twitter and there was
a bunch of folks there that had come out
of Google and at Google they were used
to using a technology that that's called
Borg at Google which is a their cluster
management system for running all their
and their applications and Twitter at
the time was a monolithic rails
application and most people call it
internally the monorail and it was a
giant yeah it's great it was a great
term yeah and and so this was this giant
Ruby on Rails app that was really really
tedious to bug really tough when you
modified it oftentimes you you would you
would cause some other part of the code
base to crash or to not work correctly
and so for lots of reasons
Twitter decided that the right thing to
do was to evolve away from this
monolithic Ruby on Rails application too
so a based based system so a
service-oriented architecture based
system so lots and lots of these smaller
services that a lot of folks are calling
micro services these days and having all
the services communicates in concert and
provide the same functionality that was
being provided in this giant monolithic
rails application so when you think
about sort of Twitter's deployment
problem in the past and it was still
great it was still a significant
deployment problem because of their
scale they had to run thousands tens of
thousands of these Ruby servers so it
was still a really tough problem but
there was pretty much one thing that you
were deploying you know you were
deploying just this this ruby app and
maybe depending on what version of it
you were deploying there was some
complexity there
it was really you know one app one way
to actually deploy it and when Twitter
started to evolve into two so uh it went
from one app to five apps to ten apps to
hundreds of apps and to thousands of
apps and the problem just became much
much tougher because the other thing
that evolved at Twitter was it went from
being Ruby to Ruby and Java to Ruby and
Java and and Scala to Ruby Java and
Scala system Python there's a little bit
of C++ there so the problem just became
significantly harder when it came to the
operations team to basically keep up
with how they could manage deploying all
these different services and it's a
tough problem to scale with humans
because basically if you had humans
managing the deployment of all these
services you kind of have to have a
bunch of people per team so they really
saw Mesa says this opportunity to be
able to have this layer where the teams
themselves could actually be responsible
for deploying their applications into
their their data center in Twitter's
case it was a data center but the same
applies if it's a cloud just you know a
bunch of machines whether they're
virtual or physical that that's you know
your data center a bunch of machines and
Twitter really really saw an opportunity
to use meso to be this this fabric to
actually do that deployment and let the
teams do it instead of actually having
to have large Operations teams managing
all of this and I think what Twitter was
doing at the time so so you asked about
contrasting the Mesa post approach from
what Twitter was doing at the time what
they were really doing at the time was
they were using a lot of puppet and hope
it was being used to basically say okay
on this machine I'm going to set this
machine up to be used for this
application and here's how everything
gets set up and that there was a lot of
manual work there and it was also kind
of creating these very very static
partitions where again it's that same
same problem that I had mentioned with
with Hadoop where you're really only
running one application per per machine
which meant that you either needed to
buy that machine to precisely fit the
application which was really really hard
because you know the amount of resources
that the application needed who knows
how many resources it needed from the
day that you started the application
which was usually when they could
a state request went in for the for the
machines to the day that the application
was actually finished and you could run
the application so I think when I first
got got to Twitter I forget how many but
there were probably something like ten
to fifteen different skews for machines
that were being purchased which also
made the operations even tougher because
there's so many different kinds of
machines with so many different pieces
of hardware that had to be managed when
one thing failed you didn't have just a
surplus of all those those replacements
for that machine you had you know just
you had to go and essentially by a
particular replacement so the whole
thing Twitter and my team we really
realized okay we could streamline this
and we could make it so you know you
could buy far fewer SKUs the
responsibility of the capacity teams
would be just making sure there's enough
capacity to run all atwitter all the
different applications the
responsibility of the meso s-- and the
aurora teams in aurora was one of these
distributed systems that we built on top
of mesas for actually deploying and
running all these applications there
sponsibility of those teams were to to
go ahead and actually schedule the tasks
across all these machines schedule the
applications across all those machines
make sure they kept running in the face
of failures and then the machines could
just kind of get plopped in the in the
cluster and then once they get that got
dropped in the cluster they got hooked
up all of a sudden they became available
resources we would just schedule across
those resources the the operations team
no longer needed to coordinate with all
the application developers on when the
machines would show up when they were
ready to be used application developers
just lost your applications whatever
available resources in the cluster would
get used even if the available resources
they were using were not in fact the
resources that had been slated for them
in the capacity planning in fact that
often was not the case it was often the
case that you would do your capacity
flying for the amount of resources you
needed for your application
but you would be able to start running
your applications immediately because we
would just have excess capacity in the
cluster already which is great so you
know you could start testing your
distributed system immediately you don't
have to wait months for four machines to
actually show up eventually those
machines would show up and they would
kind of act as the available capacity
resources for the next team that was
trying to figure out you know its its
application or trying to build it
nation and and then of course the other
big advantage was when we wanted to do
maintenance on the machines weekend
didn't have to communicate with the
application developers and say hey I in
the old days the way it used to work was
since you had the static partitions
where you used to puppet to fix the
applications to those machines when you
wanted to do any kind of maintenance on
those machines you'd have to go in and
you'd have to actually tell the
application the application teams that
were running their apps in those
machines hey I need to do maintenance
and some of your machine so I'm going to
be killing some of your machines and
which means you're going to have less
capacity for running your applications
or they'd have to figure out some kind
of dance to figure out how they could
have extra capacity during the time that
they were doing maintenance and now you
wouldn't even need to do that what you
could do instead was the office folks
could just go and they would just be
able to kill whatever jobs it what we
called actually drain the machines they
could drain the machines with those
applications we get relaunched somewhere
else in the cluster and then once the
machine was trained they could pull it
and do whatever whatever maintenance
they wanted to do whether that be
software maintenance or hardware
maintenance and so that Twitter that was
sort of the evolution of the way that
sort of sort of why there was that
evolution it was really the movement to
so uh and then sort of that the big
advantages of that evolution from having
to do so it was something like puppet or
Scheffer or what I use other tools and
this sounds like such a relief of a huge
pain point and so let's let's dive into
an example a little deeper so for
example let's say it's noon PST and you
know Twitter's getting like all this
lunchtime traffic and they have to spin
up a new instance of the application
maybe so what what's going on under the
covers is is there some kind of load
balancer that like detects something and
then it submits a request to the to the
mesos world or what exactly would happen
there in order to in order for the new
application instance to get the memory
that it needs like what's going on under
the covers yeah so so there's there's a
couple different things it depending on
the application at Twitter but basically
in a nutshell yeah we had an alerting
system which would tell you the amount
of resources that were being consumed
by any application and answer to the SLA
is that it was actually actually making
and then to depend on the application
either either human would go in and say
hey I want some more instances and then
it would use Aurora and again Aurora as
I mentioned is sort of this service
scheduler for that that we built at
Twitter and it's kind of its kind of the
past interface at Twitter that the
platform as a service interface it's
what the application developers used at
the end of the day to actually launch
your applications and they kind of
describe their applications in this
route this Python this Python esque
configuration language and they they
give that to Aurora and then Aurora
gives that to meso so in order to then
launch the tasks somewhere in the data
center where there's sufficient
resources so yeah if there was a spike
of traffic oftentimes this would occur
say when there was a big news event or
something then a team could have their
application instances immediately scaled
up to whatever free resources were
available in the cluster and so sort of
the way that we would guarantee that
there were enough resources for these
applications is we had this concept of
quota in the system and you would have
production quota and so you were all you
were always guaranteed that there was
going to be capacity in the system to be
able to scale up to to that production
quota and if that meant that we needed
to preempt or revoke resources from from
some other applications that were
running that then we would do that and
the reason why that's ok is because I
think something that a lot of people
don't really realize is there are a ton
of things that can get run in these data
centers that consume resources that you
can really easily kill so that's
everything for that's what a lot of
people typically think about which is
analytics in fact analytics might not
even be the best example because it's
sometimes you can't kill analytics
because it's really important that those
analytics job just finished because
they're doing things like showing stats
on your on your to your users about say
how many people are retweeting their
tweets or how many people are following
them or you know the amount of
engagement that they have with a
particular group of people or on
Twitter's case as well producing stats
like the number of people that
participated in a TV show last night
because of their tweets so some
analytics jobs are actually critical
production jobs but there's a ton of
other jobs that are actually running in
the data center that you can take
resources from things like build and
test you can use all these resources
these free
resources when they're not being used
for say your production front-end
traffic burning building tests all the
test jobs that you're running other you
know arbitrary things that people are
just trying out so yeah so so we could
preamp those resources we could rope
those resources if we needed to and make
sure that the production jobs would we
get their resources so they could serve
serve whatever traffic and again the way
that that works really depended on the
application whether it was done
automatically or whether the application
team itself would just go in and say oh
I need another five instances push a
button and then they'd get those
instances okay cool and so I guess talk
a little more about the in-depth
relationship between different machines
that you have spread under this meso
fabric like what what are the what are
the different roles that the machines
are playing you know you have master and
you have I think what executors and and
schedulers yeah yeah sure that's great
yeah Mesa is is sort of it's an
incarnation of what in distributed
systems we've traditionally called the
master slave architecture so what that
means is that there's a master process
and there's master nodes really and then
there's the worker nodes which are
responsible for actually managing all
the tasks that I get launched and this
is where the notion of leader election
is really important because if something
happens to the master you have to elect
a new leader to be the master you know
that's exactly right that's exactly
right so when when you run meso you
typically run three to five masters
depending on the level failure that you
want to want to actually be able to
handle and then you run whatever number
of nodes you want that actually connect
to the master and the machines
themselves that you're running the maysa
notes on those can be as homogeneous at
or as heterogeneous as you want you know
you don't have to make them all be eight
core 16-gigabyte machines you can have
some that are thirty-two core 128
gigabyte you can have some that are two
core eight gigabyte you can really mix
and match because again the goal of
meiosis is to just provide this big pool
of resources across which you want to
run all these tasks so
I I say that because you can really
organically kind of grow your cluster
you can take whatever machines you have
put them together in a cluster and then
involve that if you want to something
that looks more homogeneous per per
machine or you can keep it as
heterogeneous as as you'd like and then
they all connect to the masters and the
masters at the core of the Masters
what's called the allocator and the
allocator is what's what's responsible
for knowing about all the tasks that are
actually running in the system and
knowing what resources are free and
available and being able to then
allocate those resources to the
distributed systems that are actually
running on top so so an example of
whether those to distribute systems is
Aurora as I mentioned we have a tomato
sphere we have something that's very
similar to Aurora called marathon which
again is sort of responsible for running
these these long-lived stateless
stateless services and so in these
distribute systems that are on top the
Aurora and the marathon they have a
scheduler inside them they themselves
are what we call a framework we actually
use the word framework instead of
distributed system in meso to describe
these things that run on top and every
framework has what we call a scheduler
which you can really think of as sort of
the distributed systems coordinator it's
the thing that's trying to decide what
tasks to run and where based on whatever
resources can get allocated to it now we
call it a scheduler for a couple reasons
first if you kind of think back to the
fact that we were really sort of trying
to build something with this operating
system perspective and we wanted to
enable these distribute systems to be
able to to schedule their workloads or
schedule their tasks that's kind of the
crux of what is in one of these
distribute systems that's why we
actually call discussion or I think some
people they sort of want to hear the
word schedule they think whoa to build a
scheduler I need to have a PhD in
computer science but it's really it's
it's it's again that's the business
logic of deciding what tasks you want to
run when things fail one of the things
you might want to do so that's that's
the scheduler component and so it gets
it gets what we call resource offers
which are allocations of resource
they're an offering of resources that
the distributed system can use to
actually run its application and those
those allocations come from the
allocator that
you mentioned that runs in the master
and and it can also come from requests
that specifically come from this from
the scheduler or constraints that it
needs to actually get solves in order to
run its applications or its tasks so
just just to put a finer point on could
you give a vocab definition for for L
what a framework is and what a scheduler
is and what an executor is yeah yeah so
a framework is really just a distributed
system that runs on top of meso s-- and
the scheduler is the component that
communicates directly with meso s-- and
is given resource allocations which it
uses to decide which tasks it wants to
run throughout throughout the data
center so the task in May so it's really
the thing that we run it's the thing
that consumes resources and it's the
thing that that tells us what to do when
we actually get this thing to an
application do we run you know is it a
binary is the task represent is a binary
is it a is it a shell script you know is
it a shell command is it a docker image
these are all you know different ways
that we can actually run your tasks
until you give us you know something and
then and then we actually run that an
executor is actually it's an optional
component of a framework you can think
of a mesas framework as really primarily
being a scheduler launching tasks but it
can also be a scheduler launching tasks
which are then executed on the
individual machines by an executor so if
you don't want to you know if you want
to just give us a talk or a manager you
want to just give us a binary and you
want to say hey this is how you run my
task we can go ahead and we can just run
your task for you but if there's
something that you would like to do
that's particular to how your task gets
run and you can't code that up into our
our model then what you can run instead
is called an executor and then we'll
pass the task to your executor and say
hey here's the task that your scheduler
I told you you want to run you're the
responsible fir'd for figuring out how
you actually want to run it so you can
think of there's a lot of distribute
systems that really fit this executor
model there's there's things like like
Hadoop which has the notion of a task
tracker which is the thing that's
actually running all the machines which
is running the maps for the reduces
tracking them and then reporting their
status so that fits the executor model
really well there's also things like
spark as I mentioned which fit the
executor model
but again not every not every destroyed
system needs an executor model this is
just if you actually need it
you have that functionality in the
system so that's that's really the core
pieces there's a framework which runs on
top of Mae Sousa framework has a
scheduler scheduler on launches tasks
and if you want to sort of define how
those tasks get run then you also
implement an executor and then in order
to for these different things within
basis to be communicating you have calls
and events which is a message passing
syntax which is in contrast to for
example a request response so what's the
difference between a call slash event
and request slash response like what why
why did you choose the message passing
syntax and and how is that actualized in
a emmaus application yeah great the
reason why we chose to actually build
the system in a very actor based message
passing way is because it really forces
the person that's actually building the
the distributed system to think about
the cases when there are failures to
think about what happens if messages
don't make it through to really realize
that you can't assume this very
synchronous nature of request response
that always occurs so that was the that
was kind of kind of the kind of the
first reason so a call in in in in May
so this is a one way message send to the
meso smasher to say hey you know this is
something I'd like to do and then an
event is a one way message send from the
meso smash master back to a scheduler
which says hey here's something that has
occurred and the other reason why why we
wanted to introduce this is because
there's this concept of a basis of
events actually occurring that don't
come from the you know that they're not
something that you would get from doing
a request response they're just things
that get generated that we need to
actually send back out to schedulers so
there's there's a vet stream if you will
if things are constantly happening for
example your task has just failed a
machine where you're running tasks has
just died there are more resources
available that we'd like to allocate to
you so here you can use these resources
so these are just a synchronous things
that are occurring and so we
you need to go to just push these things
out but again we need to be able to push
these things out some of them we want to
guarantee that we always push them out
in a reliable way such as a status
update for your tasks we want to make
sure that you always find out about that
status update and other things we want
to push out into sort of a best-effort
way which is hey we tried to make this
allocation to you if we haven't heard
back from you within some period of time
we're either going to reallocate it to
you or we're gonna we're gonna allocate
it to somebody else and it's okay you
know you're distribute system itself
might be down at the time that we're
trying to push events to you because for
example maybe your distribution system
failed your schedulers failed and that's
okay you know that that happens because
failed failures occur or the machines
where your distribution system is
running have happened to crash and again
that's okay we're not going to assume
that because you have crashed all the
tasks that you've launched should also
get killed we're gonna keep them running
we're gonna assume that failures happen
okay so you're saying so you're saying
in contrast to the request/response
model the problem with the
request/response model is in the
distribute system you're gonna have some
failures and stuff and so when you if
every time one machine makes it makes a
request to another and is expecting a
response and you're maybe you're
blocking on that response it just
creates all sorts of bottlenecks you
don't have if you have the call and
event that's right that's right yeah I
mean building out a synchronous request
response distributed system these days
is also you know one that scales is a
very very very tough proposition to
actually make because of it consuming
all these resources to deal with the
blocking calls so really I think if you
think about even just on a single
machine today if we want to take
advantage of the hardware and be as
performant as possible we need to do
things in an asynchronous way that
really pushes this idea of message
passing and then that applies equally as
well to the distributed systems arena
where the systems are obviously of
course distributed and this asynchronous
message passing is really valuable and
so we just capture that in the entire
system now it doesn't mean that you
can't put abstractions on top of
asynchronous message passing to make
things look more synchronous or make
think make things look more
request/response
and plenty of folks have done that
it's just not the core of what we
actually expose them so I want to ask a
broader question we're starting to get
all these like building blocks of
distributed systems we've got all these
like Apache projects you know kafka
storm zookeeper and meso so you know
something that leverages is leveraging
these you know for example it's
leveraging zookeeper to do some leader
election and then you know you've also
got like got things like docker and so
where are we going where what is the
what is the bigger picture of what what
is a distributed system look like in
three to five years yeah that's I mean
that's a great question yeah I mean the
building blocks are also really
interesting because we're starting to
get duplicates of the building blocks
right we've got we've got zookeeper but
we've also got SCT we've got plenty of
different message queue systems out
there we've got ActiveMQ RabbitMQ gots
or some more modern replacements of
pub/sub like things Kafka's and these
and and so we're starting to get a lot
more of these things as well and where
I'd like how about I answer the question
about where I'd like to see the future
because I think it's many potential
futures but where I'd really like to see
the future of all these different
systems going is where we can start to
figure out the POSIX interface to all
these abstractions if you will these
primitives that you'd expect should be
provided any distributed or for a
distributed system so that I can just
build my application assuming that I
have a service like pub/sub or service
like a message queue or service like
coordination or service like like leader
election and I could just build it
against this interface I can build my
mum I distribute system against this
interface if in a you know if in one
organization they choose to use
zookeeper that's totally fine and if in
another organization they choose to use
NCD that's totally fine I can run my
application in both places and that's
that's what we don't really have today
that is I think really really critical
for going forward
for for our industry as a whole to be
able to be able to reuse all these
systems that that were actually using
really really effectively and when you
think about it when you think about
politics operating system today there
are a lot of things that that we take
for granted we have things like pipes so
we can we can pipe data from from one
application to to a different
application we've got a file interface
so we know we can we can share
information between applications through
files we've got the concept of processes
and we've got the concept of threads and
allocating memory and a bunch of these
things which we just use to build our
application and then for the most part
not entirely but for the most part we
can then run those applications across
any any POSIX system whether that's my
my Mac laptop or its my Linux server
machine again you know there exceptions
there are some ways in which plastics
has been bent but that basic idea of
having of having just an interface
behind which there can be many different
implementations of the actual interfaces
really really leads to us to be able to
build more applications that we can
portable and share and that's that's I
think the bigger picture of where I
really love to see the building of
distributed systems in the running of
distribute systems really go and I think
it's really powerful because today if
you build a distributed system in one
organization like say Yahoo builds
zookeeper to then go run that in in
another organization it's a lot of work
it's a ton of work to go figure out how
to make this thing work in some other
persons set up based on the way that
they've actually decided they want to do
things and it's kind of a pain in the
butt and what ends up happening it's it
ends up being enough of a pain in the
butt that another organization says you
know what this isn't worth the effort
I'm just gonna go ahead and go build my
own because turns out that would be
easier for me to do is to build my own
of this really complicated thing than to
actually figure out a way for me to be
able to run this in my own application
and I'm really looking forward to a
future world where you can build a
distributed system in one organization
and you can just start running it in
another organization as easy it is to
build a Linux app and one company and
then just start building that Linux app
in a different company and you can think
of all kinds of like great
commodification and cost savings and
like device agnosticism that comes out
of that sort of future what are the
missing pieces I mean like why what's
the disparity between where we are now
and that optimistic future well I mean
I'm obviously pretty biased but I I
think one of the big ones is really
having that that first abstraction layer
that really abstract away the machines
and provides these these primitives for
distributed systems themselves and
that's that's really what what what our
goal is with Mesa today is to be that
abstraction layer so you build all your
distributed systems on top of that and
then anybody that's running running
mesas you can they can just take the
application that they built in one
organization and then just go run it and
the other organization that's also
running mesas so a great example of that
is one of the distribute systems we
built on top of Mesa which is called
Chronos and Chronos is a distributed
cron so it's a problem that these days
is a big pain point for a lot of folks
because they'll go in and they'll set up
cron and a couple of machines and then
when that machine fails they got to go
set up at another machine and it's just
it's a really big pain in the butt
so Chronos is as a solution for that and
it only runs in mesas there's no way to
run Chronos unless you run on mesas but
the great thing about that is that was
built at at Airbnb and they read on
mesas and another organization was able
to just launch sorry a different
organization that which was also running
Mesa sauce was able to just pull down
Chronos and just deploy it in their
cluster immediately just run in the
cluster immediately it was like it was
as easy as somebody just downloading
some application for their Mac and a
better example as easy as somebody
downloading an app on their their iPhone
or on Android and just double-clicking
it and running it that's incredible yeah
and and i think that that's missing
layer that's that abstraction layer
which really gives people the ability to
build these things and then just go run
them in their their data centers so that
i think is one of the biggest things i
think though the second thing is i mean
getting that is fantastic but getting to
that place we really need to continue to
to fill out all the things that are
really necessary to build these
distributed systems on top of mesas and
make what I was talking about at the
beginning of this chat really really
easy right you know the goal of Mesa is
to make it easier to build distribute
systems by abstracting away tough things
like dealing with failures dealing with
actually distributing tasks dealing with
leader election and I would say to be
quite honest that we're not
100% there you know we're not at the
point where it is I mean it's still
pretty easy to build Cronos but we need
to make it even easier you know I think
the example here is a lot of people
don't use threads because it's sort of
the lower level the lower level
abstraction it's that it's you know it's
a good abstraction to expose but it's a
lower level and you need even higher
level abstractions on top of threads and
that's one of the things that we're
really doing with meso sand at Mesa
Square today is saying okay this is the
first step in just making it easier to
build the distribute systems by exposing
the program the primitives but we're
going to make it even easier to use
those primitives with higher-level
SDKs and higher level level level things
on top and I think that's going to make
it that's going to make even more people
want to build distribute systems on top
of something like mesos and and then
they're gonna see the benefits of doing
that as wow I can then just take my
distribute system that I built here and
I can run it someplace else I think a
lot of people are really excited about
that because you know we're a big hacker
community and we like to share the work
that we did and we like to be able to
build something and let other people got
to be able to take advantage of it
that's great so um where can people go
to find out more about pesci mesas and
find out more about you yeah cool so um
there's a couple places you can go to
meso stat Apache org which is the the
website for the Apache masters project
you can also go to Mesa sphere comm and
we've got a bunch of documentation there
we even expose a lot of pre-built
packages for meso so that you can
download right from the Mesa sphere
website and for me I would say you can
follow me on twitter my handle is at Ben
H and that's usually a good way to reach
out if you're looking to chat with me
great
well Ben Heineman thank you so much for
coming on software engineering radio
could talk to you for another two hours
it's great great material yeah thanks so
much for having me it's been great
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radio now to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you